Welcome back. In this video,
we're going to discuss
project closing.
We'll answer the questions,
what does project closing mean,
why is it important, and
when does it occur?
Project closing consists of
the process performed to
formally complete the project,
the current phase, and
contractual obligations.
The first thing you should
know is that completing
a project is not the same
thing as closing a project.
Just because a project is done
doesn't mean it's closed.
In a restaurant, just
because you've ordered
your meal and finished it,
doesn't mean your dining
experience is over.
You have to pay the
bill before you leave.
It's the same idea with projects.
What does it actually take
for a project to be closed?
There are three criteria that
make up a project closing.
You'll want to assure
all work is done.
Ensure that the agreed upon
project management processes are
executed and get formal
recognition from
stakeholders that
the project is done.
First, you must assure
all work is done.
There's a chance one of
your tasks may have
been overlooked.
Let's say there was a
change made that called for
reprioritizing work
during the project.
For instance, when your team
completed user acceptance testing
for Project Plant Pals,
everything was finished
and wrapped up.
But months later, a
customer searches for
allergy information
about the plants
on Office Green's site,
but that information is
nowhere to be found.
If you did a review before
wrapping the project,
you might have found
that this task,
creating allergy
documentation, was
overlooked and therefore
not completed.
In doing a review of the project,
you double- and triple-check
that all work is
done to avoid having to
revisit the project later on.
Next, you must ensure
that all agreed
upon project management
processes are executed.
Sometimes, managerial
tasks get overlooked.
If the task itself is finished,
the procedural or
administrative work that
needs to take place afterwards
might slip your mind.
An example might be
getting contracts
signed and processed.
It might have been months since
the project was completed,
but when you revisit the contract
with your plant provider,
you realize that neither of you
ended up actually signing it.
This is a crucial misstep that
leaves both parties
vulnerable, and
it's now taking place way after
the new services official launch.
Finally, you'll need
formal recognition and
agreement that the project is
complete by key stakeholders.
If you don't have
formal approval from
all stakeholders that
a project is over,
certain stakeholders
may still request
adjustments to the project
because they'll think
it's still active.
This may affect various
members of your team.
For instance, if
Office Green's
contracted web developers
believe that the
project is still active,
they may still be dedicating
time and even billing hours
of work on this project,
which means wasted money
for Office Green.
In the same way that all of
the previous phases of
the process, like
initiation, planning,
executing, monitoring, and
controlling serve a purpose,
closing serves its own,
equally important purpose.
Closing a project is
important because it
ensures that nothing has
fallen through the cracks.
If a project isn't closed,
your team's efforts,
time, and credibility may
be negatively impacted.
To avoid negative
impacts to your team,
there are a couple of
different types of
projects that you'll want
to know about and avoid.
These are the
never-ending project
and the abandoned project.
The never-ending project exists
when, for whatever reason,
the project deliverables and
tasks cannot be completed.
This may occur when tasks are
delegated to team
members who don't have
the skills necessary
to complete the tasks
or when deadlines aren't
properly communicated,
maybe when user
acceptance testing yields
too many non-launch
blocking bugs,
or when your client
is unsatisfied,
despite meeting
their requirements.
Pay special attention to
protecting the scope
of your project,
and you're much more likely to
close a project successfully.
If it feels like the
customer wants much more
from you than this project
is slated to deliver,
maybe the best option
is to commit to
a follow-up project and
close the current one.
The abandoned project exists when
inadequate handoff of the
project deliverables occurs.
Basically, the final deliverable
never makes it to your customer.
It wouldn't make sense
to build a product and
then not be able to
market it or sell it.
Making plans to ensure
an adequate handoff or
transition deliverables is
crucial to ensure customers are
happy and projects
are properly closed.
In summary, you'll want to do
everything you can
to properly close
a project because
it may leave you
on the hook for
incomplete contracts,
incomplete scope, or
non-compliant practices.
In the next video,
we'll discuss the necessary
steps included in
a comprehensive closing process
for clients and stakeholders.